<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-03T00:02:45+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Manoj Manduva</title><subtitle>My blog aka &apos;Mind Meets Machines&apos; is a collection of thoughts, stories and comments on topics like philosophy, neuroscience, design, technology and people.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cosmos as a conscious being</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos-as-a-conscious-being.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmos as a conscious being" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos%20as%20a%20conscious%20being</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos-as-a-conscious-being.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/cosmos.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
I think, Cosmos is a conscious being. It could think, feel and do just like us. Probably has more senses than we possess.</p>

<p>We are limited by our senses. Our perception of reality is suitable to our survival. We see the range of spectrum where it matters to us. Just like few insects can only smell to find its mate. We see to find our food and flee from our predators and similarly our limited 5 senses.</p>

<p>We think consciousness resides in our brain. Is it a memory? Is it a thought? an Electric signal? A chemical reaction? I don’t know. May be we are limited by our senses to know it.</p>

<p>But, it is the thing which reminds us that we exist.</p>

<p>There is a possibility that there could be more information, more messages hidden in this universe from our plain sight.</p>

<p>I always felt, Earth is an organism too. It breathes, it goes through cycles of seasons, maintains a balance and timing.</p>

<p>But it could be extended to the whole universe.</p>

<p>If there is some disturbance, everything is adjusted to bring balance, just like a living being.</p>

<p>The rising global temperatures were a concern and a balance is brought through a rogue virus.</p>

<p>How is everything so beautifully connected ?</p>

<p>A conscious being is well connected and is aware of the past and the future and can take actions to bring back the balance and do a course correction.</p>

<p>In the cell division , parent divides into daughters and so on. They even mutate and transform to other living organisms. And, so we are here.</p>

<p>In Big Bang, the universe was formed from one single source of high density and high temperature. Do you see the connection?</p>

<p>If the children ( we or entire living organisms ) have a conscious , the parent might have been definitely conscious. The dark matter could also be conscious.</p>

<p>Cosmos is conscious.</p>

<p>“The only dominant theory we have of consciousness says that it is associated with complexity — with a system’s ability to act upon its own state and determine its own fate.”Chandra X-Ray Observatory Center / NASA/CXC/SAO</p>

<p>Dig deep?</p>

<p>https://www.nbcnews.com/mach/science/universe-conscious-ncna772956</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think, Cosmos is a conscious being. It could think, feel and do just like us. Probably has more senses than we possess.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Never lose few people</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never lose few people" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/mirror.png" alt="My helpful screenshot" /> <br />
Wisdom is taking decisions to your advantage.</p>

<p>It might be moving to new city, or taking a new job or starting something on your own or ordering a meal.</p>

<p>Problems are thrown at us day in and day out. To solve them is to break them down to smaller chunks and taking micro decisions.</p>

<p>The ability to solve the problems depends on our knowledge of the reality we are in.</p>

<p>The more we are aware, conscious and connected with the reality the more equipped we are to solve any problem.</p>

<p>The day we are blinded to the reality, we lose our power to take wise decisions.</p>

<p>The reasons we are cut off from the reality are :</p>

<ol>
  <li>Not having a different perspective or at least listening to those who have.</li>
  <li>Ego, too much invested in our own opinions and avoiding others who offer a different opinions from ours.</li>
  <li>Admitting mistakes and learning we don’t know.</li>
</ol>

<p>True friends are those who offers clean mirror to your behaviors and actions.</p>

<p>They are not afraid to offer a different perspective and honest opinions at the risk of losing your friendship.</p>

<p>I‘m fortunate to have a handful since my early days.</p>

<p>I have seen many others who despise them because they hold a different view from theirs.</p>

<p>We should have the courage to admit when we don’t know. It gives the opportunity to learn something new. Add to the understanding of the reality.</p>

<p>We need not simply buy in to their opinion.</p>

<p>If I‘m stuck to any principle in life it is ‘Sapere Aude‘ loosely translates to dare to think. It means that one should have the courage to think on their own, act on their own and own up the consequences. It is true freedom.</p>

<p>Having a different perspective offers a good vantage point to think better, understand the reality better and adapt to the reality to act better.</p>

<p>There are few who offer this different perspective and empower you to solve the toughest problems in your life.</p>

<p>Never lose few people.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>In 1992 I found a friend who offered a new perspective of not following the popular bunch in my class but maintain a new idea of restraining from using any swear words.</p>

<p>In 1999, I found a friend who criticized me for my lazy attempt in a Math examination which motivated me to top the class and eventually set a trajectory to where I’m today.</p>

<p>In 2006, I found a friend who put a mirror to my financial behavior and offered timely help from an impending crisis.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wisdom is taking decisions to your advantage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stranger Things — Part2 : The ride</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranger Things — Part2 : The ride" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/ride.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
I can’t bend my right knee beyond a point, after I met with an accident in 2002 I had PTS (Post Traumatic Stress) where my cartillege hardened while healing a fracture.</p>

<p>The accident happened when I was riding a motorbike with my friend Srikanth on a particular road from our college to house. It was not the regular route we take everyday.</p>

<p><b>The road is less travelled, literally.</b></p>

<p>Hardly people use it to get to the city from this far off place where our college is located. It had a character of its own.</p>

<p>Have you ever had some association with any routes like this? Maybe your route to school which you took as a child or the route you used to take to work everyday. It is interesting how these routes evoke few strange memories when you take them again later.</p>

<p>It happened with me after 2 years.</p>

<p>I had a dream of going on that road like that, again on a bike. This time Srikanth was driving and I was on backseat. After going some distance on this lonely road, we had to stop.</p>

<p>There was a huge fort wall like structure exactly across the road. Strange! I thought. I went close, looked up and touched the stone wall. There was no one near by. We were worried and took a U turn.</p>

<p><b>I heard a big thunder. I was shaken a bit and I woke up.</b></p>

<p>After few weeks, comes one of the interesting days of my life. The day that has answered many questions of my life which I had at that time like confidence, creativity, friendship, pride, trust and also started a chapter of strange events.</p>

<p>All of us were exhausted on the long day of 1st campus placements. We had tests, group discussions, interviews till evening for the 2 companies that visited us. There was some time before we gathered to hear out the results. Srikanth and myself thought of catching some fresh air.</p>

<p><b>You guessed it. We started the bike to go on that lonely road.</b></p>

<p>It didn’t take me long to realise the exact scenes repeating from my dream. Same weather, same time. I was almost waiting to see what happens next.</p>

<p>I was expecting to see the wall.</p>

<p>I heard the thunder.</p>

<p>It started raining heavily.</p>

<p>We didn’t want to stop anywhere but took a U turn , so that we don’t miss the anouncement. I didn’t find the wall, but just an old house near by.</p>

<p>—</p>

<p>I got selected and so is Srikanth and other friends.</p>

<p>Since then this phenomenon of dreams extending into reality repeated for couple of more times and then stopped.</p>

<p>But I always leave my door open, to <b>Stranger Things</b> in life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I can’t bend my right knee beyond a point, after I met with an accident in 2002 I had PTS (Post Traumatic Stress) where my cartillege hardened while healing a fracture.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Should I Work?</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Should I Work?" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/glitch.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
To pay bills?</p>

<p>To buy new things?</p>

<p>To take new loans?</p>

<p>To save money for the future?</p>

<p>To be secure?</p>

<p>To enjoy the time off when not working?</p>

<p>To see new places?</p>

<p>To find the next job?</p>

<p>To utilize time?</p>

<p>To not waste time?</p>

<p>To seek satisfaction?</p>

<p>To be relevant?</p>

<p>To earn some respect?</p>

<p>To learn new things?</p>

<p>To create new things?</p>

<p>To improve things around us?</p>

<p>To make new relationships?</p>

<p>To make life better for the people around?</p>

<p>To contribute to the world’s prosperity?</p>

<p>To solve the world’s miseries?</p>

<p>To meet the world’s expectations?</p>

<p>Why should I work?</p>

<p>To care for me?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To pay bills?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first post</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first post" /><published>2023-10-26T21:47:24+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T21:47:24+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/123.png" alt="My helpful screenshot" /> <br />
Hello World!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></summary></entry></feed>