<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-26T05:23:06+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Manoj Manduva</title><subtitle>My blog aka &apos;Mind Meets Machines&apos; is a collection of thoughts, stories and comments on topics like philosophy, neuroscience, design, technology and people.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dream it. See it. Do it.</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2025/01/25/dreamit-seeit-doit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dream it. See it. Do it." /><published>2025-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2025/01/25/dreamit-seeit-doit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2025/01/25/dreamit-seeit-doit.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/close.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br /></p>
<h2>Dream it. See it. Do it.</h2>
<p><br /></p>
<h4>Power of Visualization.<br /></h4>
<p><br /></p>

<p><b>Cool breeze.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>I vomit. The excruciating pain is making my head dizzy. Everything is turning into a blur. I try hard to stop moving my right leg, and slowly the world stops spinning. Things become clearer. Now I can feel the cool breeze. Now I’m hungry. Sri opens the tiffin box. There are idlis with coconut chutney fusing them. We are both hungry. He feeds me the first bite. It feels strange to be fed by a friend. I’m shy. I say I’m good; I can have it. We spend an hour finishing the food slowly, taking every gulp without moving an inch in my lower body. Sri leaves me to find water from a nearby building or factory. There is nothing else nearby. Why did I end up here? Under the tree? In the mid-afternoon? Let us see how the day started.<br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Unlearn.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>Today is an exam day at college. The day is calm, bright, and beautiful. We can come home in the afternoon after the exam. It means there will be fewer buses operating at noon, so we decide to take the new bike. It is the bike I bought after pestering my parents for months: a brand-new Hero Honda Splendor. I’ve ridden it a couple of times with Dad and another friend. I’m new to riding a geared motor vehicle; however, I’m used to gearless scooters. I take the keys, lock the house, and off we go. I’m referring to some notes on the way while Sri is driving. We finish the exam. The code executes perfectly, and I answer all the questions in the viva well. While coming back home, I want to ride. I want to take a new route. The route is a long way, deserted mostly. I encounter an unexpected S-shaped bend, I mistakenly pull the clutch thinking it’s the brake and lose control. I go straight ahead and fall into a ditch, narrowly missing a nasty granite pillar fencing a paddy field. My right leg twists, and I hear a crackling sound. Our brains are so strongly wired by practice. It’s unlearning that is most difficult. The reflexes of gearless scooters kick in, sensing impending danger.<br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Guilt.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>What follows next are hours of agony and pain. I lie in bed, looking at the spinning fan. My dad comes into the bedroom, looks at me, and says nothing. The pain of my fractured right knee at the upper tibia is less compared to the guilt. He says he would spend time with me over the weekend to practice more. But I was in haste. The next 45 days I’m confined to bed. I miss the following six final exams that year. I miss going out with friends. I’m ashamed. I want to get back on the road as soon as possible.<br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Power of Visualization.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>I question myself: why did I make such a blunder? I imagine how I would do it differently if I were in that situation again. I lucid dream about how I would start riding my bike. I construct scene by scene how I would take the bike out, carefully sit on it, turn the key, pull the kick rod, kick-start it, pull the clutch, change the gear, and slowly release the clutch while giving throttle. There is this fine balance where the clutch is half-released when the bike starts to move forward, when you need to give a gentle throttle. I imagine that phase over and over again. After 45 days, when I am barely walking without support, I ask my mom if I can go out and ride the bike. She says yes!</p>

<p><b>Back on the Road Again.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>I take the bike out and do exactly as I imagined. It is smooth. I enjoy every bit of riding the bike. I can feel the gentle breeze on my face. I never look back. I am surprised at how everything goes so naturally as if I have been riding the bike forever. I enjoy riding my bike until I take my car out after five years without telling my parents. But that’s a story for another day. I realize the power of visualization right then. What you dream and visualize repeatedly, where you give your genuine focus, the whole universe conspires to manifest it. Things are bound to happen. Buddha said, “What you think, you will become.<br /> What you feel, you attract.<br />What you imagine, you create.” <br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Double-Slit Experiment.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>And it is not some romantic idea you want to believe, that visualization helps you manifest things. Physicists performed an experiment called the Double-Slit Experiment, where they passed electrons through two slits and found interference patterns on the screen. It means they behave as waves. But when they give attention to the electrons the next time, they hit the screen exactly in the position of the slits, as if they behave like particles. I feel all the things you want are around you as invisible waves waiting to become real.<br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Not a One-Time Wonder.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>It doesn’t happen just once. While I have all the time lying in bed, I see repeated events of visualization being manifested multiple times in my life, sometimes knowingly or unknowingly. As a child, I prepare for a test to get into a good school in my town. My sister tells me there is a train track beside the school. I am immediately attracted to the idea of a passing train and visualize seeing trains pass by from my class window. It motivates me to push myself to practice more. Later, I get through the test and relive all the imaginations. Later, I visualize many times in my life with a clear focus on the outcomes, and I eventually materialize those things.<br /><br /></p>

<p><b>Limiting Beliefs.<br /><br /></b></p>

<p>But why don’t we visualize that often? Ironically, our very life gets in the way. We are too busy to stop, dream, and visualize. Either with our own self-limiting beliefs, we can’t dare to visualize and realize its power. We can remind ourselves to visualize more with honest intentions by setting a time in the day.<br /><br /></p>

<p>By the way, I pass all 13 exams on consecutive days at once from the year I missed due to the accident and the next one.<br />Happy visualization!<br /><br /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dream it. See it. Do it. Power of Visualization.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmos as a conscious being</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos-as-a-conscious-being.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmos as a conscious being" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos%20as%20a%20conscious%20being</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/cosmos-as-a-conscious-being.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/cosmos.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
I think, Cosmos is a conscious being. It could think, feel and do just like us. Probably has more senses than we possess.</p>

<p>We are limited by our senses. Our perception of reality is suitable to our survival. We see the range of spectrum where it matters to us. Just like few insects can only smell to find its mate. We see to find our food and flee from our predators and similarly our limited 5 senses.</p>

<p>We think consciousness resides in our brain. Is it a memory? Is it a thought? an Electric signal? A chemical reaction? I don’t know. May be we are limited by our senses to know it.</p>

<p>But, it is the thing which reminds us that we exist.</p>

<p>There is a possibility that there could be more information, more messages hidden in this universe from our plain sight.</p>

<p>I always felt, Earth is an organism too. It breathes, it goes through cycles of seasons, maintains a balance and timing.</p>

<p>But it could be extended to the whole universe.</p>

<p>If there is some disturbance, everything is adjusted to bring balance, just like a living being.</p>

<p>The rising global temperatures were a concern and a balance is brought through a rogue virus.</p>

<p>How is everything so beautifully connected ?</p>

<p>A conscious being is well connected and is aware of the past and the future and can take actions to bring back the balance and do a course correction.</p>

<p>In the cell division , parent divides into daughters and so on. They even mutate and transform to other living organisms. And, so we are here.</p>

<p>In Big Bang, the universe was formed from one single source of high density and high temperature. Do you see the connection?</p>

<p>If the children ( we or entire living organisms ) have a conscious , the parent might have been definitely conscious. The dark matter could also be conscious.</p>

<p>Cosmos is conscious.</p>

<p>“The only dominant theory we have of consciousness says that it is associated with complexity — with a system’s ability to act upon its own state and determine its own fate.”Chandra X-Ray Observatory Center / NASA/CXC/SAO</p>

<p>Dig deep?</p>

<p>https://www.nbcnews.com/mach/science/universe-conscious-ncna772956</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think, Cosmos is a conscious being. It could think, feel and do just like us. Probably has more senses than we possess.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Never lose few people</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never lose few people" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/never-lose-few-people.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/mirror.png" alt="My helpful screenshot" /> <br />
Wisdom is taking decisions to your advantage.</p>

<p>It might be moving to new city, or taking a new job or starting something on your own or ordering a meal.</p>

<p>Problems are thrown at us day in and day out. To solve them is to break them down to smaller chunks and taking micro decisions.</p>

<p>The ability to solve the problems depends on our knowledge of the reality we are in.</p>

<p>The more we are aware, conscious and connected with the reality the more equipped we are to solve any problem.</p>

<p>The day we are blinded to the reality, we lose our power to take wise decisions.</p>

<p>The reasons we are cut off from the reality are :</p>

<ol>
  <li>Not having a different perspective or at least listening to those who have.</li>
  <li>Ego, too much invested in our own opinions and avoiding others who offer a different opinions from ours.</li>
  <li>Admitting mistakes and learning we don’t know.</li>
</ol>

<p>True friends are those who offers clean mirror to your behaviors and actions.</p>

<p>They are not afraid to offer a different perspective and honest opinions at the risk of losing your friendship.</p>

<p>I‘m fortunate to have a handful since my early days.</p>

<p>I have seen many others who despise them because they hold a different view from theirs.</p>

<p>We should have the courage to admit when we don’t know. It gives the opportunity to learn something new. Add to the understanding of the reality.</p>

<p>We need not simply buy in to their opinion.</p>

<p>If I‘m stuck to any principle in life it is ‘Sapere Aude‘ loosely translates to dare to think. It means that one should have the courage to think on their own, act on their own and own up the consequences. It is true freedom.</p>

<p>Having a different perspective offers a good vantage point to think better, understand the reality better and adapt to the reality to act better.</p>

<p>There are few who offer this different perspective and empower you to solve the toughest problems in your life.</p>

<p>Never lose few people.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>In 1992 I found a friend who offered a new perspective of not following the popular bunch in my class but maintain a new idea of restraining from using any swear words.</p>

<p>In 1999, I found a friend who criticized me for my lazy attempt in a Math examination which motivated me to top the class and eventually set a trajectory to where I’m today.</p>

<p>In 2006, I found a friend who put a mirror to my financial behavior and offered timely help from an impending crisis.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wisdom is taking decisions to your advantage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stranger Things — Part 1 : The meeting</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranger Things — Part 1 : The meeting" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part1.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/meeting.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
<b>…So there was this big old auditorium with plush red seats. I was the only one standing at the very first row from the top having a complete view of the wide dark empty space. It was something so grand and old , clearly I have never been there earlier.</b></p>

<p>By the way,</p>

<p>Do you think Past influences future or does future influence the past?</p>

<p>For example, we know a living thing like a plant will eventually die. So is it behaving in such a way that it dies of old age? Or because it is behaving in such a way, that eventually it dies.</p>

<p>Ok let me try another example. We all are going through the COVID crisis now. Do you think, it is happening because of our unsustainable choices in the past? or because the humanity is bound to go extinct someday, we are preparing to lead our lives like this.</p>

<p>One of the explanation of Reality is this causality loop between Past and Future.</p>

<p><b>There was water dripping slowly from the roof of this auditorium. I think I was waiting there for someone. Otherwise I wouldn’t be there. Just before I was turning impatient and a little scared.</b></p>

<p>I saw someone entering the door.</p>

<p>There is a cusp between the future and the past. Where you cannot point out if the past has extended itself to future or the future has arrived little early.</p>

<p>It could be a blip. A bug in the 4th dimensional space time.</p>

<p>Ok, may be I’m starting to lose you.</p>

<p>I want to say, that there are some strange events that you cannot explain.</p>

<p><b>Oh! My friend. My class mate from school. But what was he doing there. I wasn’t expecting him. Actually I wasn’t expecting anyone or anything to happen. I haven’t seen him in the last 10 years since I left the school nor did I have a chat.</b></p>

<p>We believe only what we imagine to be possible. Our imagination is also limited. You could extend it only if you are deliberate. It is a hard exercise. Otherwise everyday we drift on a superficial level with the flow of possibilities.</p>

<p>It is like you light up a candle in the dark of an unknown house.You see only your room and hardly the corners. Probably you can imagine what it is like in the rest of the house. But it is beyond imagination what lies outside the realm of light.</p>

<p>Science tries hard to imagine and explain. But it is also limited by the light from candle.
<b>
I was happy to see him. We shook hands.</b></p>

<p>And I woke from my sleep. It was a dream. Gosh.</p>

<p>It was a strange dream. Someone whom I never met for last decade, appears in your dream. What does it mean?</p>

<p>I know as a student of science, it sounds funny. But I always keep myself open for some stranger things.&lt;/b&gt;</p>

<p>At least I had to after that day.</p>

<p>I got a call few weeks later.</p>

<p>It is him from NIT Jaipur. Was visiting Hyderabad. Wanted to stay in our house.</p>

<p>He was there with me for 5 days.</p>

<p>Note: Based on a true incidents from my life</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[…So there was this big old auditorium with plush red seats. I was the only one standing at the very first row from the top having a complete view of the wide dark empty space. It was something so grand and old , clearly I have never been there earlier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stranger Things — Part2 : The ride</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranger Things — Part2 : The ride" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/stranger-things-part2.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/ride.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
I can’t bend my right knee beyond a point, after I met with an accident in 2002 I had PTS (Post Traumatic Stress) where my cartillege hardened while healing a fracture.</p>

<p>The accident happened when I was riding a motorbike with my friend Srikanth on a particular road from our college to house. It was not the regular route we take everyday.</p>

<p><b>The road is less travelled, literally.</b></p>

<p>Hardly people use it to get to the city from this far off place where our college is located. It had a character of its own.</p>

<p>Have you ever had some association with any routes like this? Maybe your route to school which you took as a child or the route you used to take to work everyday. It is interesting how these routes evoke few strange memories when you take them again later.</p>

<p>It happened with me after 2 years.</p>

<p>I had a dream of going on that road like that, again on a bike. This time Srikanth was driving and I was on backseat. After going some distance on this lonely road, we had to stop.</p>

<p>There was a huge fort wall like structure exactly across the road. Strange! I thought. I went close, looked up and touched the stone wall. There was no one near by. We were worried and took a U turn.</p>

<p><b>I heard a big thunder. I was shaken a bit and I woke up.</b></p>

<p>After few weeks, comes one of the interesting days of my life. The day that has answered many questions of my life which I had at that time like confidence, creativity, friendship, pride, trust and also started a chapter of strange events.</p>

<p>All of us were exhausted on the long day of 1st campus placements. We had tests, group discussions, interviews till evening for the 2 companies that visited us. There was some time before we gathered to hear out the results. Srikanth and myself thought of catching some fresh air.</p>

<p><b>You guessed it. We started the bike to go on that lonely road.</b></p>

<p>It didn’t take me long to realise the exact scenes repeating from my dream. Same weather, same time. I was almost waiting to see what happens next.</p>

<p>I was expecting to see the wall.</p>

<p>I heard the thunder.</p>

<p>It started raining heavily.</p>

<p>We didn’t want to stop anywhere but took a U turn , so that we don’t miss the anouncement. I didn’t find the wall, but just an old house near by.</p>

<p>—</p>

<p>I got selected and so is Srikanth and other friends.</p>

<p>Since then this phenomenon of dreams extending into reality repeated for couple of more times and then stopped.</p>

<p>But I always leave my door open, to <b>Stranger Things</b> in life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I can’t bend my right knee beyond a point, after I met with an accident in 2002 I had PTS (Post Traumatic Stress) where my cartillege hardened while healing a fracture.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Should I Work?</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Should I Work?" /><published>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2024/09/02/why-should-i-work.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/glitch.png" alt="cover image" /> <br /><br />
To pay bills?</p>

<p>To buy new things?</p>

<p>To take new loans?</p>

<p>To save money for the future?</p>

<p>To be secure?</p>

<p>To enjoy the time off when not working?</p>

<p>To see new places?</p>

<p>To find the next job?</p>

<p>To utilize time?</p>

<p>To not waste time?</p>

<p>To seek satisfaction?</p>

<p>To be relevant?</p>

<p>To earn some respect?</p>

<p>To learn new things?</p>

<p>To create new things?</p>

<p>To improve things around us?</p>

<p>To make new relationships?</p>

<p>To make life better for the people around?</p>

<p>To contribute to the world’s prosperity?</p>

<p>To solve the world’s miseries?</p>

<p>To meet the world’s expectations?</p>

<p>Why should I work?</p>

<p>To care for me?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To pay bills?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first post</title><link href="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first post" /><published>2023-10-26T21:47:24+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T21:47:24+00:00</updated><id>https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manojmanduva.com/mind/2023/10/26/my-first-post.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/123.png" alt="My helpful screenshot" /> <br />
Hello World!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mind" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></summary></entry></feed>